<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.8.13">
  <compounddef id="citelist" kind="page">
    <compoundname>citelist</compoundname>
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <detaileddescription>
<para><variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_abbott-qir-06"/>[1]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para>J.<nonbreakablespace/>Abbott. <ulink url="http://www.dima.unige.it/~abbott/">Quadratic interval refinement for real roots</ulink>, 2006. Poster presented at the 2006 Int. Symp. on Symb. and Alg. Comp. (ISSAC 2006).</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_beh-eeeafcs-05"/>[2]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para>Eric Berberich, Arno Eigenwillig, Michael Hemmer, Susan Hert, Lutz Kettner, Kurt Mehlhorn, Joachim Reichel, Susanne Schmitt, Elmar Sch<oumlaut/>mer, and Nicola Wolpert. Exacus: Efficient and exact algorithms for curves and surfaces. In Gerth<nonbreakablespace/>S. Brodal and Stefano Leonardi, editors, <emphasis>13th Annual European Symposium on Algorithms (ESA 2005)</emphasis>, volume 3669 of <emphasis>Lecture Notes in Computer Science</emphasis>, pages 155<ndash/>166, Palma de Mallorca, Spain, October 2005. European Association for Theoretical Computer Science (EATCS), Springer.</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_cgal:bhkt-risak-07"/>[3]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para>Eric Berberich, Michael Hemmer, Menelaos<nonbreakablespace/>I. Karavelas, and Monique Teillaud. Revision of the interface specification of algebraic kernel. Technical Report ACS-TR-243301-01, INRIA Sophia-Antipolis, Max Planck Institut f<uumlaut/>r Informatik, National University of Athens, 2007.</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_ek-exact-08"/>[4]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para>Arno Eigenwillig and Michael Kerber. Exact and efficient 2d-arrangements of arbitrary algebraic curves. In <emphasis>Proceedings of the Nineteenth Annual ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA08)</emphasis>, 2008. 122<ndash/>131.</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_ekw-fast-07"/>[5]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para>Arno Eigenwillig, Michael Kerber, and Nicola Wolpert. Fast and exact geometric analysis of real algebraic plane curves. In Christopher<nonbreakablespace/>W. Brown, editor, <emphasis>Proocedings of the 2007 International Symposium on Symbolic and Algebraic Computation (ISSAC 2007)</emphasis>, pages 151<ndash/>158, 2007.</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_eigenwillig-phd-08"/>[6]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para>Arno Eigenwillig. <emphasis>Real Root Isolation for Exactand Approximate Polynomials Using Descartes &apos; Rule of Signs</emphasis>. PhD thesis, Universit<aumlaut/>t des Saarlandes, Saarbr<uumlaut/>cken, Germany, 2008.</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_grlr-sturm-habicht-98"/>[7]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para>L.<nonbreakablespace/>Gonzalez-Vega, T.<nonbreakablespace/>Recio, H.<nonbreakablespace/>Lombardi, and M.-F. Roy. Sturm-habicht sequences, determinants and real roots of univariate polynomials. In B.F. Caviness and J.R. Johnson, editors, <emphasis>Quantifier Elimination and Cylindrical Algebraic Decomposition</emphasis>, Texts and Monographs in Symbolic Computation, pages 300<ndash/>316. Springer, 1998.</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_kerber-phd-09"/>[8]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para>Michael Kerber. <emphasis>Geometric Algorithms for Algebraic Curves and Surfaces</emphasis>. PhD thesis, Universit<aumlaut/>t des Saarlandes, Saarbr<uumlaut/>cken, Germany, 2009.</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_cgal:lpt-wea-09"/>[9]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para>Sylvain Lazard, Luis Pe<ntilde/>aranda, and Elias Tsigaridas. Univariate algebraic kernel and application to arrangements. In Jan Vahrenhold, editor, <emphasis>SEA</emphasis>, volume 5526 of <emphasis>Lecture Notes in Computer Science</emphasis>, pages 209<ndash/>220. Springer, 2009.</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_cgal:r-mpfi"/>[10]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://perso.ens-lyon.fr/nathalie.revol/software.html">MPFI - the multiple precision floating-point interval library</ulink>. Revol, Nathalie and Rouillier, Fabrice.</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_cgal:mt-mpfr"/>[11]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://mpfr.org">MPFR - the multiple precision floating-point reliable library</ulink>. The MPFR Team.</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_cgal:rz-jcam-04"/>[12]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para>Fabrice Rouillier and Paul Zimmermann. Efficient isolation of polynomial&apos;s real roots. <emphasis>Journal of Computational and Applied Mathematics</emphasis>, 162(1):33<ndash/>50, 2004.</para><para></para></listitem>
<varlistentry><term><anchor id="_1CITEREF_cgal:r-rs"/>[13]</term></varlistentry>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.loria.fr/equipes/vegas/rs/">RS - A software for real solving of algebraic systems</ulink>. Rouillier, Fabrice.</para><para></para></listitem>
</variablelist>
</para>    </detaileddescription>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
